Guide to the Merton H. Miller Papers 1941-2002
University of Chicago Library
- Series III: University of Chicago
  - Subseries 2: Writing and Research
    - Conference material, 1995-1996 (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - "Why Does Everyone Keep Bad-Mouthing Derivatives?" drafts, research material and organizational material, 1997 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - "The Chicago Financial Economics Tradition, Some Practical Lessons," presented at the 448th Convocation, drafts, notes and program, 1997 (Box 63, Folder 6)
    - "The Graduate School of Business of the University of Chicago, The Last Hundred Years and the Next," presented at the Graduate School of Business Centennial Gala, drafts and notes, 1997 (Box 63, Folder 7)
    - Peter J. Tanous, Investment Gurus, "Merton Miller," 1997, drafts, 1996 (Box 63, Folder 8)
    - Nai-Fu Chen, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1997 (Box 63, Folder 9)
    - China, notes and organizational material, 1997 (Box 63, Folder 10)
    - "Financial Markets and the Welfare of Nations," presented at the Celebration of the 35th Anniversary of the Frankfurt International School, drafts, research material and organizational material, 1996-1997 (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - Speech given to New York alumni, drafts, 1997 (Box 64, Folder 2)
    - Clearinghouses, notes and research material, 1997 (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - Speech given at New York University, notes and conference material, 1997 (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - Speech given at Zentrum für Unternehmungsführung, Frankfurt, drafts and conference material, 1997 (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - "Some Investment Non-Advice, GSB Style," presented at the Chief Executives Organization Conference, Chicago, drafts and conference material, 1997 (Box 64, Folder 6-7)
    - "The History of Finance, An Eyewitness Account," keynote address presented at the Fifth Annual Meeting of the German Finance Association, Hamburg, drafts, 1998 (Box 64, Folder 8)
    - "A Tribute to Myron Scholes," presented at the Nobel Memorial Prize Luncheon of the American Economic Association, drafts, notes and research material, 1997-1998 (Box 64, Folder 9)
    - "Some Reflections on the EMU," keynoted address presented at the Euro Conference in Brussels, drafts and research material, 1998 (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - "Lessons for Venezuela from the Current Southeast Asia Financial Crisis," drafts, notes and research material, 1998 (Box 64, Folder 11)
    - Speech given at Gleacher Center Dinner, notes and guest lists, 1998 (Box 64, Folder 12)
    - "Turkey and the European Monetary Union," presented at the celebration of the 40th Anniversary of the Faculty of Administrative Sciences of Bogaziçi University, Istanbul, drafts, research material and organizational material, 1998 (Box 64, Folder 13)
    - Foreword, Money and the Nation State (edited by Richard Timberlake, Jr. and Kevin Dowd), 1998, drafts and promotional material, 1994-1995 (Box 65, Folder 1-2)
    - Long-term capital management, research material, 1997-1998 (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Nai-Fu Chen, correspondence and research material, 1998 (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - Ben C. Ball and Sam L. Savage, "Holistic vs. Hole-istic Exploration and Production Strategies," draft, 1998 (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - Speech given in Stockholm, notes and organizational material, 1998 (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Keynote speech presented at the BARRA Rogers-Casey 1998 Research Seminar, Newport, Rhode Island, drafts and organizational material, 1998 (Box 65, Folder 7)
    - Speech given in Poland, drafts, research material and organizational material, 1998 (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Honorary degree, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, drafts, research material and organizational material, 1998 (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - "The Orange County Bankruptcy and Its Aftermath, Some New Evidence" (with David J. Ross), 1997, drafts and research material, 1996-1997 (Box 65, Folder 10-13)
    - Management conferences, Graduate School of Business, drafts, research material and organizational material, 1992-1999 (Box 66, Folder 1-4)
    - Pacific Basin Finance Conference, drafts, research material and organizational material, 1990-1999 (Box 66, Folder 5-10)
    - Pacific Basin Finance Conference, drafts, research material and organizational material, 1993-1999 (Box 67, Folder 1-3)
    - Corporate Hedging in Theory and Practice, Lessons from Metallgesellschaft (with Christopher L. Culp), 1999, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1994-1995 (Box 67, Folder 4-11)
    - Corporate Hedging in Theory and Practice, Lessons from Metallgesellschaft (with Christopher L. Culp), 1999, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1993-1994 (Box 68, Folder 1-5)
    - "China and the World Trade Organization, Some Ancient Legends Updated," drafts, notes and research material, 1999 (Box 68, Folder 6)
    - "Incentive Schemes for Portfolio Managers," keynote address presented at the Conference on Research, Risk and Regulation in the Hedge Fund Industry, Duke University, drafts, notes and research material, 1999 (Box 68, Folder 7)
    - Hermann Meyer zu Selhausen, drafts, correspondence and research material, 1999 (Box 68, Folder 8)
    - "From Markowitz to Sharpe to Black-Scholes," presented at the Panel on Research and Practice in Financial Markets, Carnegie-Mellon University, drafts, notes and organizational material, 1999 (Box 68, Folder 9)
    - Michael Milken, presentation material, 1999 (Box 68, Folder 10)
    - Keith Sharfman, correspondence and interview transcript, 2000 (Box 68, Folder 11)
    - Derivatives Strategy Hall of Fame, correspondence, 1999 (Box 68, Folder 12)
    - Bruce D. Grundy, editor, Selected Works of Merton H. Miller, 2002, notes, bibliographical material and editorial material, ca. 2000-2002 (Box 68, Folder 13-14)
    - Speech given at American Economic Association meeting, drafts, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 1)
    - Afterword, "The Court is Now in Session!" draft, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 2)
    - "Is the U.S. Economy Headed for a Financial Collapse?" drafts and notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 3)
    - Conferences in Asia and New Zealand, notes, conference material and presentation materials, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 4)
    - Law School Forum, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 5)
    - Turkey, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 6)
    - China, charts, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 7)
    - Clemson University, research material and transparencies, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 8)
    - Tano Santos, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 9)
    - Innovations, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 10)
    - Banking reform, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 11)
    - Stewart C. Myers, "Merton H. Miller's Contribution to Financial Economics," draft, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 12)
    - Alumni speech given in Turkey, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 13)
    - Executive Program speech, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 14)
    - Harper Dinner speech, drafts and notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 15)
    - Speech given in Thailand, drafts and conference material, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 16)
    - Speech given in Hamburg, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 17)
    - Speech given at Latin School, notes, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 18)
    - "Financial Innovation," speech given in Virginia, ca. 1990s (Box 69, Folder 19)
    - Drafts and reprints, ca. 1950s-2000 (Box 69, Folder 20-21)
    - Drafts and reprints, ca. 1950s-1990s (Box 70, Folder 1-6)
    - Drafts, reprints and clippings, ca. 1980s-1990s (Box 71, Folder 1-8)
    - Drafts, publications and reprints, ca. 1980s-2000 (Box 72, Folder 1-10)
  - Subseries 3: Correspondence
    - Sub-subseries 1: Subject File
      - Modigliani-Miller research, 1962 (Box 73, Folder 1)
      - Franco Modigliani, 1962-1963 (Box 73, Folder 2)
      - William F. Sharpe, 1962-1963 (Box 73, Folder 3)
      - John Hirshleifer, 1963 (Box 73, Folder 4)
      - Willard I. Zangwill, 1964 (Box 73, Folder 5)
      - Franco Modigliani, 1964-1966 (Box 73, Folder 6)
      - Belgium, 1966-1967 (Box 73, Folder 7-8)
      - Referee requests and reports, 1964-1969 (Box 73, Folder 9)
      - Referee reports, ca. 1960s (Box 73, Folder 10)
      - Publication offers, 1970-1971 (Box 73, Folder 11)
      - DeWitt C. Dearborn, 1972 (Box 73, Folder 12)
      - Securities Investor Protection Corporation, 1972 (Box 73, Folder 13)
      - Richard V.L. Cooper, 1975 (Box 73, Folder 14)
      - Bell Journal of Economics, 1976 (Box 73, Folder 15)
      - Patrick J. Hess, 1979-1981 (Box 73, Folder 16)
      - Permissions, 1979-1981 (Box 74, Folder 1)
      - Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1981 (Box 74, Folder 2)
      - George A. Poole, 1983-1984 (Box 74, Folder 3)
      - George C. Philippatos, 1984 (Box 74, Folder 4)
      - Carnegie-Mellon University, 1985 (Box 74, Folder 5)
      - Fred D. Arditti, 1986 (Box 74, Folder 6)
      - Society for the Promotion of Financial Studies, 1986-1987 (Box 74, Folder 7)
      - Thomas H. Dittmer, 1987 (Box 74, Folder 8)
      - Hermann Göppl, 1987 (Box 74, Folder 9)
      - Russell Sage Foundation, 1988 (Box 74, Folder 10)
      - Basil Blackwell, 1988 (Box 74, Folder 11)
      - Journal of Banking and Finance, 1988-1990 (Box 74, Folder 12)
      - Journal of Finance, 1989 (Box 74, Folder 13)
      - Prudential, 1989 (Box 74, Folder 14)
      - Review of Financial Studies, 1989 (Box 74, Folder 15)
      - Charles W. Upton, 1989 (Box 74, Folder 16)
      - Requests for reprints, 1980-1990 (Box 74, Folder 17)
      - Joel Seligman, 1989-1990 (Box 74, Folder 18)
      - Peter L. Bernstein, 1990-1991 (Box 74, Folder 19)
      - Bank One Corporation, 1991 (Box 74, Folder 20)
      - Basil Blackwell, 1991 (Box 74, Folder 21)
      - Journal of Business, 1982-1991 (Box 74, Folder 22)
      - Journal of Political Economy, 1980-1992 (Box 74, Folder 23)
      - Journal of Financial and Quantitative Analysis, 1987-1992 (Box 74, Folder 24)
      - Review of Financial Studies, ca. 1988 (Box 74, Folder 25)
      - Leo Melamed, 1981-1992 (Box 74, Folder 26)
      - Fischer Black, Nobel Prize nomination, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 27)
      - Referee report, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 28)
      - Susan Chaplinsky, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 29)
      - Doris Wan Cheng, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 30)
      - Robert Comment, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 31)
      - Toshiya Kawamura, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 32)
      - Thomas Flannigan, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 33)
      - Peat Marwick, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 34)
      - Jiang Wei, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 35)
      - Richard A. Werner, 1993 (Box 74, Folder 36)
      - Financial Markets International, 1962-1994 (Box 74, Folder 37)
      - J.P. Morgan Securities, 1994 (Box 74, Folder 38)
      - Claudio Loderer, 1994 (Box 74, Folder 39)
      - Fischer Black Fund, 1995 (Box 74, Folder 40)
      - Bill Clinton, 1995 (Box 75, Folder 1)
      - Permissions, 1981-1996 (Box 75, Folder 2)
      - American Economic Review, 1989-1996 (Box 75, Folder 3)
      - John Wiley and Sons, 1991-1996 (Box 75, Folder 4)
      - Blackwell Publishers, 1991-1998 (Box 75, Folder 5)
      - New York University, 1994-1998 (Box 75, Folder 6)
      - Journal of Applied Corporate Finance, 1998 (Box 75, Folder 7)
      - Rogério Ortega, 1998 (Box 75, Folder 8)
      - World Innovation Foundation, 1998 (Box 75, Folder 9)
      - Francis Lui, 1999 (Box 75, Folder 10)
      - Permissions, 1996-2000 (Box 75, Folder 11)
      - Blackwell Publishers, 2000 (Box 75, Folder 12)
      - Hugo J. Faria, 1997-2000 (Box 75, Folder 13)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Chronological File
      - 1965-1969 (Box 75, Folder 14-17)
      - 1970-1979 (Box 76, Folder 1-15)
      - 1980-1990 (Box 77, Folder 1-15)
      - 1990-2000 (Box 78, Folder 1-13)
  - Subseries 4: Administration
    - Center for Mathematical Studies in Business and Economics, memoranda, proposals and brochure, 1962 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Honorary degrees, recommendations and biographical material, 1965 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, fellowship material, 1969 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Examining Committee on the Graduate School of Business, report, 1969 (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - Admission and graduation requirements for the MBA degree, memoranda, 1969 (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - Committee on the Appointment of Ralph E. Gomory, report, 1969 (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - Econometrics program proposal, memoranda, course material and program descriptions, 1970 (Box 79, Folder 7)
    - Summer programming, memoranda, research material and program material, 1970 (Box 79, Folder 8)
    - Faculty meetings, memoranda, 1970 (Box 79, Folder 9)
    - Subcommittee on Isaac Ehrlich, report and correspondence, 1971 (Box 79, Folder 10)
    - Subcommittee on Fischer Black, report, correspondence and biographical material, 1971-1972 (Box 79, Folder 11)
    - Western Electric Fund Awards, nomination material, 1972-1973 (Box 79, Folder 12)
    - Committee on Term Associate Professorships, reports, notes and clippings, 1973 (Box 79, Folder 13)
    - Committee on Term Associate Professorships, reports and biographical material, 1973 (Box 79, Folder 14)
    - Subcommittee to Consider Promotion for Robert Z. Aliber, reports, correspondence and biographical material, 1973 (Box 79, Folder 15)
    - Committee on Faculty Size and Composition, memoranda, reports and study data, 1976 (Box 79, Folder 16)
    - Honorary degrees, recommendations and biographical material, 1977-1978 (Box 79, Folder 17)
    - Committee on the Future of the Executive Program, memoranda and notes, 1978 (Box 79, Folder 18)
    - Dean Witter Foundation, correspondence and proposals, 1981 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Committee to Recommend Candidates for the Chicago Mercantile Professorship, memoranda, 1984 (Box 80, Folder 2-3)
    - Subcommittee on Sanford Grossman, correspondence and report, 1986 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - University of Chicago Management Conference, correspondence and brochure, 1987 (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - Dean's Advisory Committee on MBA Students and the Curriculum, correspondence, reports and research material, 1988-1989 (Box 80, Folder 6)
    - University of Chicago Centennial, list of proposed conferences, 1990 (Box 80, Folder 7)
    - University of Chicago Centennial, Graduate School of Business planning committee, correspondence, proposal and list of Ph.D. alumni, 1990 (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - Robert C. Merton, honorary degree recommendations, biographical material and correspondence, 1991 (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - Finn E. Kydland, proposal to the National Science Foundation for course and curriculum development in neoclassical macroeconomics, 1993 (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - Fischer Black Fellowship, correspondence, drafts and biographical material, 1995 (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - Süleyman Chair in Ottoman History, correspondence and drafts, 1995-1996 (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - Alumni development, correspondence, 1996 (Box 80, Folder 13)
    - Scheduling forms, undated (Box 80, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 5: Arrangements for Speaking Engagements
    - 1969-1984 (Box 80, Folder 15-19)
    - 1983-1990 (Box 81, Folder 1-18)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 82, Folder 1-25)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 83, Folder 1-25)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 84, Folder 1-20)
    - 1993-1997 (Box 85, Folder 1-11)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 86, Folder 1-9)
    - 1998-2000 (Box 87, Folder 1-7)
  - Subseries 6: Video Recordings
    - Item 1: Unidentified, 1986 (Box 87)
    - Items 2-3: Nobel Prize, awarding and news coverage, ca. 1990 (Box 87)
    - Items 1-2: Nobel Prize, awarding and news coverage, ca. 1990 (Box 88)
    - Item 3: "The Silent Stars," 1990 (Box 88)
    - Item 4: "New Strategies for Maximizing Shareholder Value," conference highlights, 1992 (Box 88)
    - Item 5: "Inside Financial Derivatives," keynote speech, Risk Management Symposium, Chicago Mercantile Exchange, 1994 (Box 88)
    - Items 6-7: "Interview," Chicago Mercantile Exchange, 1994 (Box 88)
    - Item 8: "Chicago Board of Trade," CNBC-TV, 1997 (Box 88)
    - Item 9: "University of Chicago Graduate School of Business June-July Asia Tour," Burson Marsteller, 1999 (Box 88)
    - Item 10: "Nobel Prize Winner Merton Miller Dies," Ahead of the Curve, CNN, 2000 (Box 88)
    - Item 12: "Press Conference," undated (Box 88)
    - Item 22: "Keynote Speech," undated (Box 88)
    - Item 13: "CENTER," Pedagogisch Technische Hogeschool, undated (Box 88)
- Series IV: Consulting and Professional Activities
  This series contains material related to Miller's activities outside of teaching, research and speaking in the university context. These activities included participation in professional organizations; service on advisory, editorial and governing boards; and consulting for corporations and law firms. This series is divided into three subseries to distinguish among the types of material, and levels of organization and restriction.
  Subseries 1: Alphabetical File, contains correspondence, administrative records, publications, and drafts, organized according to the names of organizations in which Miller participated. Much of the material in this subseries relates to Miller's service on advisory and editorial boards of professional organizations and academic journals. Documents from his service as president of the American Finance Association is included here (related material is also found in Series III: Subseries 2).
  Subseries 2: Government Documents, contains material such as briefs, statements, testimonies, and transcripts, most from court cases in which Miller served as a witness.
  Subseries 3: Restricted, relates to Miller's work as a consultant, and contains proprietary and confidential information related to legal cases and corporate financing. The names of corporations and law firms that engaged Miller's services are given when identified.
  - Subseries 1: Alphabetical File
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1989 (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - American Finance Association, 1974-1990 (Box 89, Folder 2-8)
    - Allied Social Science Association, 1975 (Box 89, Folder 9)
    - Center for Business and Policy Studies, 1997 (Box 89, Folder 10)
    - Chicago Board of Trade, 1984-1987 (Box 89, Folder 11)
    - Chicago Council on Foreign Relations, 1988 (Box 89, Folder 12)
    - Chicago Mercantile Exchange, 1979-1986 (Box 89, Folder 13-14)
    - Chicago Mercantile Exchange, ca. 1990s (Box 90, Folder 1-3)
    - China Financial Weekly, 1993 (Box 90, Folder 4)
    - Econometric Society, 1988-1989 (Box 90, Folder 5)
    - Financial Economists Round Table, 1992-1995 (Box 90, Folder 6-7)
    - Globex, 1988 (Box 90, Folder 8)
    - Group of Thirty Derivatives Project, 1992-1993 (Box 90, Folder 9-10)
    - Industry Summit, 1996 (Box 90, Folder 11)
    - Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, 1994 (Box 90, Folder 12)
    - International Association of Financial Engineers, 1995-1998 (Box 90, Folder 13)
    - Japan and the World Economy, 1987 (Box 90, Folder 14)
    - Journal of Corporate Finance and Governance, 1992 (Box 90, Folder 15)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1993 (Box 90, Folder 16)
    - National Association of Realtors, 1983 (Box 90, Folder 17)
    - National Bureau of Economic Research, 1993-1998 (Box 90, Folder 18)
    - National Science Foundation, 1985-1989 (Box 90, Folder 19)
    - New Palgrave Dictionary of Money and Finance, 1989-1990 (Box 90, Folder 20)
    - University of Iowa Board of Visitors, 1984 (Box 90, Folder 21)
    - University of Minnesota, 1987 (Box 90, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 2: Government Documents
    - Court documents, 1972-1999, Amerada Hess Corporation, et al. v. State of Alaska Bank United of Texas v. United States of America (Box 90, Folder 23-24)
    - Court documents, 1997-1999, California Federal Bank v. United States of America Glendale Federal Bank v. United States of America LaSalle Talman F.S.B. v. United States of America (Box 91, Folder 1-5)
    - Court documents, 1997-1999, Bank United of Texas v. United States of America Bluebonnet Savings Bank, F.S.B. v. United States of America California Federal Bank v. United States of America C. Robert Suess, et al. v. United States of America (Box 92, Folder 1-5)
    - Court documents, 1999, Bank United of Texas v. United States of America California Federal Bank v. United States of America (Box 93, Folder 1-2)
    - Chicago and North Western Transportation Company, statements before the Interstate Commerce Commission, 1977 (Box 93, Folder 3-4)
  - Subseries 3: Restricted
    - Legal material, corporate material and correspondence, 1980s- 1990s, Argentaria Bank United of Texas Chicago Board of Trade Chicago Mercantile Exchange Commonwealth Edison Long-Term Capital Management Metallgesellschaft Corporation New York Stock Exchange State of Illinois Wunsch Auction Systems (Box 94, Folder 1-22)
    - Legal material, corporate material and correspondence, 1970s- 1990s, Adobe Oil and Gas Corporation California Power Exchange Corporation Chicago Mercantile Exchange Commonwealth Edison GTE Service Corporation Lexecon Montgomery Ward and Company National Association for the Advancement of Colored People National Cheese Exchange Schiff, Hardin and Waite Unocal (Box 95, Folder 1-24)
    - Legal material, corporate material and correspondence, 1960s- 1990s, ATT Crédit Agricole Indosuez Continental Bank New York Stock Exchange Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom Standard Oil Tellefsen Consulting Group (Box 96, Folder 1-21)
    - Legal material, corporate material and correspondence, 1970s- 1990s, Bank United of Texas Bluebonnet Savings Bank Crédit Agricole Indosuez Glendale Federal Bank LaSalle Talman Bank Monolith Portland Cement Company Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton and Garrison Winnebago Industries Unidentified (Box 97, Folder 1-25)
    - Legal material, corporate material and correspondence, 1970s- 1980s, Chicago Board of Trade Winnebago Industries (Box 98, Folder 1-11)
    - Chicago Board of Trade, legal material, corporate material and correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 99, Folder 1-3)
- Series V: Personal
  This small series contains copies of Miller's CV from 1982, an incomplete list of publications from around the time of Miller's death, birthday party memorabilia, and material related to an alumni beer-tasting event at which Miller presided.
  - Curriculum vitae and lists of publications, 1982-2000 (Box 100, Folder 1)
  - Birthday party speech and memorabilia, ca. 1993 (Box 100, Folder 2)
  - GSB Club, beer tasting at Weinkeller Brewery and Restaurant, invitation, notes and menu, 1994 (Box 100, Folder 3)